Rhiannon: Children’s human rights
are the basic things, that children
need to thrive, they need to be
free and live with dignity and be
protected from violence or abuse.
They should have an adequate standard
of living, the right to education, to
play, be healthy, and be cared for.
Leah: Children need to have their own
rights over and above ‘human rights’
related to adults, because they are
separate and unique to adults, and need
special protection because of their
vulnerability and developing maturity.
They are often less articulate than
adults and have special developmental
needs and evolving capacities and are
less likely to be taken seriously.
Rhiannon: Once a child or young person
develops mental health concerns those
human rights can become more of an
issue, but they are no different.
Children and young people are entitled
to respect for their privacy and
confidentiality, for example, in
getting advice and counselling on
mental health matters, depending
on their age and understanding.
Leah: Many of the aims of services
helping children and young people
who are experiencing mental health,
emotional and psychological issues,
align with human rights values.
These include supporting young
people to be involved in their
care and treatment plans.
Children and young people should be
treated with dignity and respect in their
interactions with services, and it should
be ensured that family members or carers
are able to participate in discussions.
Rhiannon: All children with mental
health issues need to be protected
from violence, abuse, stigma and
mistreatment in institutions such as
health and social care facilities,
schools and the criminal justice system.
Any ‘seclusion’ or ‘isolation’ of a
young person against their will or
without parental consent, especially
where the young person lacks competence
or capacity to consent, could lead
to potential human rights issues.
Leah: Seclusion or isolation should only
really be used as a last resort, and
not as a punishment or way to encourage
good behaviour, as this could have a
serious impact on the young person.
Children’s best interests should
always be central, taking action
to enable all children and young
people to have the best outcomes.